[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software do you know how to code are you
looking to supplement your income level
up your career or gain AI experience
have you answered yes to any of these
questions check out data annotation data
annotation pays you to train AI models
by solving and reviewing coding problems
from home on your own schedule apply now
at data annotation. Tech programmers
that's data annotation. Tech programmers
or use the application Link in the
episode description on the SEO website
at se-
radio.net this is Sam tagert for
software engineering radio I'm here
today with lellan Falco lellan is an
agile technical coach and
internationally renowned speaker he is
the creator of approval tests co-author
of the mob programming guide book and
co-founder of teachingkids programming.
org Lan is here to talk to us about
approval testing today we have talked
about testing on many previous episodes
such as 516 with Brian Ain on P test 431
with Ken yunes Clark on using unit
testing for teaching and if you do way
back in our archives with Kent back
talking about the history of unit
testing way back in in episode 167 so
welcome Luan I'd like to start by just
discussing the general testing landscape
and and how developers are testing their
code today and how approval testing fits
into that whole landscape well so it's a
large landscape right and I tend to
straddle two very extreme sides of it
right so as you mentioned like I'm the
creator of approval test and so we do a
lot of work in the open source world and
usually on approval tests Al though I
work on some other projects as well and
in that world testing works really well
right like so we're doing test First
Development I have like a standard
python mob that meets every Sunday and
we usually do about two hours of work
and in that two hours we usually release
a feature and I mean like finish and
release right so every two hours we are
like pushing a new version of the
software out to piy likewise like like I
have a a guy I meet up with Lars for the
Java approvals and we pair and we can
usually do a feature in two hours as
well right and then again that gets
released to Maven immediately so that is
the tests are great the code is easy to
work with the whole devops pipeline is
in place and these things support each
other right like I wouldn't feel safe to
release so quickly if I didn't have my
test there really like protecting me and
telling me hey it's okay to do this
that's not the only thing right like
there's a whole other section to devops
that do that but also you know in that
world we have like dependabot and if
somebody updates a dependency we detect
it immediately and automatically and
then we get the PLL request and because
we have good tests our test will run and
if our test run it will automatically
merge so like when log for J came out we
didn't even notice right like they
released the patch our system detected
It upgraded and released without us
knowing but the other side of that is
the clients that I work with right so
I'm a technical coach and what that
means is like companies bring me in and
we sit with their programmers and we
program together and we learn to program
better but the thing is like the
companies that bring me in are never the
companies that are doing really really
well right like they're always companies
that are struggling it's really
unfortunate like if you look in like the
World of Sports the athletes that get
the most coaching are the people who are
at top of their field right like Kevin
feder is amazing and and he has like 12
coaches right like it's just like a
whole ecosystem taking the people who
are the best and making them even better
but very often that doesn't happen in
software like if you're doing okay or
you're doing good were like okay we'll
leave you alone and it it's when they're
struggling that we're like okay now now
we'll send in help yeah I had a very
interesting conversation with a friend
of mine I was complaining about a
specific framework and how all the
projects I got that were written in that
framework were horribly written and he
he made the comment well if they were
well written they wouldn't have called
you so I thought that was kind of fun
exactly right and so that there I'm
seeing the opposite side and and on that
side almost universally everybody has
tests they might not have tests in a
specific project but they definitely
have tests like if you if you were to
zoom back out right like say there's the
company has like a 100 projects probably
like 50 70 of them have tests of of some
sort some places so like like a client I
was in earlier this year they were using
Sonos and Sonos does a lot of code
metrics and will gate the checkins and
they would not allow you to check in new
code if it didn't have coverage but a
lot of their code was not designed in a
way that the tests were really helpful
for the engineers and so we wrote some
code and we split it up and we tested it
and we knew that it worked and we used a
thing called executable command tests
which are really powerful tests but they
don't really increase your code coverage
because the idea is like they are
acceptance level tests right so like you
can imagine the nice thing about
acceptance level tests is they sort of
like they're systemwide and they do this
great thing they give you a lot of
assurance that the thing works but
they're very hard to set up and and
conduct and keep consistent I was just
going to interject and ask about code
coverage because I want to make sure
that our audience understands exactly
what we're talking about so when you say
code coverage what do you mean right so
code coverage is a misleading term it is
the percentage of lines that are
executed when you run a test and
unfortunately the word implies that
these lines are covered or protected in
some sort of way that's not the case you
could write tests that you know run
something and then an exception gets
thrown and then it catches the exception
and swallows it and doesn't assert or
verify anything and that would be great
test coverage right but it it doesn't in
any way protect you but it's an easy
thing to measure and measurements and
metrics are really important to managers
and so a lot of this stuff gets done and
so we would write these tests and
literally we' call them test to
increased code coverage right and they
they were horrible tests right they
didn't protect us in any way but what
they allowed us to do is commit our code
because we knew everything underneath it
was covered and was safe and like this
is the part that we needed to not cover
right but we couldn't not cover it
because Sonos would complain and we were
at least honest about it right we're
like okay Sonos is forcing us to do this
let's let's call these tests to increase
code coverage but then when I would move
and work with other teams I would seek
tests that were not called that that
seem to have important names like tests
to verify the system is calling the sub
projects correctly or subsystems
correctly but they wouldn't right all
they were doing was increasing the test
coverage too and in those systems where
the names were less honest I think the
developers thought that's what testing
was right like test is something you do
to fulfill a safety checkbox when you're
are writing code there's more and more
like okay I enjoy the podcast and I know
that everyone here who's listening is
mainly a developer right which is
unfortunate because the problem I'm
about to talk about usually is not
something that Developers create it's
something that developers are are part
of right but they're they're sort of out
of their part but a lot of the
developers who continue to actually like
improve themselves through their career
grow up and and become managers at some
point and so if I am talking to someone
out there who in the future becomes a
manager I hope like this part resonates
and you remember but there is this huge
problem I'm seeing of shared and split
pain right and most of the time the
people who design the system are trying
to separate things to make him sort of
optimal but the moment you split pain
you cause problems and so like to just
leave code for a moment I have a friend
Rodney who unfortunately got diagnosed
with cancer last October like it's
horrible right it's stage four cancer
but a couple months ago I went over to
seeum and I had really hurt my knee I
enjoy swing dancing and I had maybe done
a little too much of it and my knee was
just really hurting now Rodney would
swap me his cancer from my hurt knee
like like any day of the week but it was
really hard for me to empathize on his
cancer while my knee was hurting right
because it's my knee it's his cancer but
it's my knee and I'm always going to
preference my pain and I see this in
companies a lot where it's like okay
what is the thing that I need to do so I
can say I'm doing my job right and maybe
as a manager it's like I need to make
sure that I can say look at the test
coverage that we have and the developers
are saying I need to check that box in
so I can commit the code and then what
gets lost in that separation is that the
tests are supposed to be helping like in
my open source I am my boss right I'm
not writing tests for somebody else I'm
writing tests because they make my life
faster and easier like I'm solving my
pain and the moment that that gets
separated and the pain is created one
where and solved somewhere else like
that gets us into a lot of trouble I see
this in Dev Ops right like there used to
be Dev and Ops and the dev would write
bugs but Ops would have to like deal
with them on the weekend and people are
like oh we should take that split pain
and put it together and we'll create
this thing called devops and now the
developers who write the bugs are also
the people who are responsible for like
deploying it and now that pain is shared
we start solving it and then companies
were like oh this devops seem seems
really good we should make a devops team
and now you've separated the pain again
right so a lot of times I see teams that
are writing tests because they're
supposed to
but they're not doing it to solve their
own pain and if you're writing tests not
to solve your own pain those tests are
not really helping you it's not like
you're lazy or or have bad intent it's
just the Dynamics of a system you should
be solving pain that you feel and people
who are like and there's a lot of
advocates for test first or test driven
development and all those people who are
really like advocating it it's because
they're using tests to solve their pain
and I see that but I don't see it that
often because I'm a consultant so most
of the time I see places that are
writing tests to solve someone else's
pain and those tests tend to not be very
good so to bring us back around to
approval testing how does approval
testing help you write tests that solve
your pain well okay so for my pain so so
I'm going to take this from like the
good place right so testing in general
right like you'll see three different
things the most common thing I think is
arrange act assert right that came from
the original unit testing place
and the idea here was like you arrange
some stuff you act on some stuff and
then you you write this assert and the
asserts were always sort of check that
one is is the value or check that the
name is Sam or you know some very
primitive data but like spot checking
and then bdd came along this was from
Dan North and he was like the words are
very important and and I don't like this
arrange act assert so we're going to use
given when then and it Maps right
directly to range act assert and it
still has the same we're going to spot
check these these little places with
approval tests it moves to just you do
something and then you verify right so
I'm going to do something that's my
action of the test and then I need to
verify the result and honestly like if
it is just a simple number or a very
small string I still use asserts like
they're great but very often it's not
like very often it's like I want to set
something up and then I want to validate
this customer or I want to validate this
transaction
or I want to validate the received call
right like this Jason object and so
approval tests allows you to validate
more complicated things and it does it
by printing the result so if it's Jason
you'll usually just sort of pretty print
it sometimes it will filter like the
printing is important right so like
maybe you have stuff like timestamps in
there right and like those are not going
to be consistent and so you'll like you
won't print those or you'll filter them
out or goids or another like thing like
that right so you you print the thing
you care about and then you look it you
you save it to a file and you look at
the file and you say oh this is what I
want and then you save it and you those
files actually get saved so we'll here
this go by approval testing I've heard
it called Golden Master testing but
actually the thing I've heard the most
now is Snapshot testing right and that's
because just is a very popular framework
and it uses a similar type of mechanism
so basically you form some action you
take a snapshot of the data that that
action returns whether it's an object or
some hierarchy or collection or whatever
it happens to be and then what do you do
with that data once you get it you store
it to a file store it to a file okay and
then the next time you run the test what
what happens so one of two things either
it matches or it doesn't match if it
matches nothing happens like your test
pass there are no interactions
everything is happy but if it doesn't
pass now we need to ask some questions
like why doesn't it pass right and so
depending on how you've printed that
object it would be nice to get some
assistance on seeing that right so by
default approvals has a thing called
reporters and reporters are they come
from a tool I used to use a lot when I
was on Windows called slick run so slick
run was like this little Runner that
would just sit in the bottom and it
would launch programs right and it was
really really powerful and to me growing
up in a Windows ecosystem slick run was
the thing that let me see the power of
combining different pieces of software I
think people who grew up in Linux they
got that on the command line right
because it's really really common to
like do something and then pipe it into
another command and pipe it into another
command right that's just how Linux
works but in Windows it doesn't work
that way but slick run was the thing
that made me realize that and so in
approv approvals is the same thing so
let's say that I'm writing a piece of
HTML right I could hand it off to a
reporter that opens up a diff tool right
like maybe Beyond Compare and it shows
me here's the old HTML and here's the
new HTML and then it'll it'll zoom in
because that's what Beyond Compare does
and show hey these three lines changed
right those values that used to be here
are now here and then I can look at that
and say hey that that's cool I like that
but maybe that's not what I'm interested
in maybe I'm interested in like how this
page renders right so maybe instead I'll
report by launching it out to Chrome and
it will actually render the web page and
I can say oh yeah that looks good or you
can do like a more complicated reporter
right like you could have it run out to
a headless browser and take snapshots so
it ends up with pgs of how the website
works in three different formats right
so like if it's on a browser if it's on
a phone or if it's on a tablet and now I
might want to pull it up in an image
diff comparison because when I'm looking
at two different images it can be very
hard I don't know if you ever play those
games when you're a kid where you had
two pictures and it's like spot the six
differences that's really hard to do as
a human but as a computer it's really
easy like you just use an image diff
tool and so my point being that
depending on how I want to understand
what has changed I might use a different
tool an approval test is set up to open
that tool and help me understand it once
I understand it I still a choice because
maybe maybe I'm fixing a bug in which
case the behavior should change right
and so it failed because the behavior
changed test lock Behavior so the old
behavior is no longer in play but the
new behavior is what I actually want so
now that I understand the change maybe I
I'm like okay that's great let me fix
the approval file which is just moving
it over just copying the file over or
maybe I've introduced a bug maybe I've
unintentionally change something and now
I need to go back to my software and fix
that right now I have a question you are
checking in those approval files into
your source code control correct so as
you change things if you accidentally
changed more than you wanted you could
go back at a later point and look at
those and somehow see that yeah so you
can do two things you can you can a say
like oh I didn't so let's say like you
change some stuff and you accidentally
make a piece of code hidden that should
have been shown right or you make the
color wrong you you didn't notice and
you you approve the file anyways so you
can actually go through your your Source
control and be like Ah that's where it
happened you can actually see the change
it's almost like using get BCT right you
can just do it through history but the
other thing that you can do which is
really nice is let's say that you're
doing some UI work right we've also seen
this happen a lot in Jason right but in
both of these things it seems like
they're simple enough like the pictures
of the UI in the way that like the Json
is formatted is simple enough that
product owners can understand those
images right or those those files and so
what we'll see is product owners going
into Version Control and like literally
opening up the image and drawing a red X
over like the thing they want to fix and
then they'll like just submit it and all
of a sudden your test break right and
and now you have a broken test that is a
feature request
hm right and then like you'll run it
it'll be like oh wait and it's handr
right so it's never like that's going to
be the thing that you approve but it is
more than enough information for you to
say okay I know what I need to fix and
then when you fix it you just move the
fixed copy over again and that is like a
very nice way of communicating intent so
question then so my understanding of
approval testing was it was basically
taking whatever data you had and
flatting it to a string and wrri it to a
text file but also works with binary
files the predominant way that I do it
you could also do it with a binary file
okay so you could have you run it
through your printer and your printer
renders the HTML generates your images
and stores them somewhere and then that
works too yeah and in fact you can do a
step so like I don't know if you're
familiar with a code Retreat actually I
should ask are you familiar with code
Retreats I know what they are I've never
one so for the audience if you haven't
so this is the thing Cory Haynes started
about oh 2009
and it's a group of people get together
in person usually although that has
changed a bit during the pandemic and
they spend the day doing a single
exercise over and over with different
languages different people and different
constraints and it's just a way to like
I think of it like a yoga meditation
retreat but for code right it's really
like a nice thing but often they'll do
this thing called Game of Life Game of
Life a Comm Game of Life is sort of this
simulation so you have a board of cells
and the cells will come alive or die
based on different rules and has some
really neat behaviors and like for those
we will very often use approval tests
and in the beginning we'll usually start
with text and we'll be like hey let's
get a board and let's get this cell and
let's see how it changes there are just
a text file but it's like a storyboard
right so it's like here's what the board
looks at frame one and here's what the
board looks at frame two but as we start
to get more advanced on this we'll
actually turn this into graphics and
then the approved file is an animated
gift
and you can actually see here's a board
and here's this very complicated like a
100 sequences of the board growing and
dying and and that would be really
complicated to do well in normal unit
testing it would be almost impossible to
do right show me how like this blob
transforms across a grid of a 100 over
100 like that's just almost impossible
to do with the CTS it's possible to do
if you stream it to a text file but it's
still a lot to like understand you have
to move through the things but in an
animated gif it's super easy to
understand and it's a two-line test
right because the do is set up this
board and then the verify is just verify
this board for 100 sequences it's two
lines of code and so because the tests
are easy to write I write them and
because the tests give me insight into
what's going on I keep them and they
they help me right and there's that
balance of how hard is a to write versus
how much value is it giving me and so
even if it gives me a lot of value we'll
use numbers of value I don't sure what a
value unit is but let's say it gives me
a 100 units of value right but it takes
150 units to write like I'm not gonna do
that because I'm lazy and it's now it's
causing me pain it's not solving me pain
but if it only cost me two and it gives
me 100 then I'm doing it so it doesn't
matter how much protection it's giving
me right it matters how much pain
it's saving me as I'm listening this I'm
really trying to contrast it with like
my traditional unit testing mentality
and it seems like you're taking a step
back like unit testing is very detailed
and focused and it's like I run this
function I get this specific output and
I'm verifying like one specific value or
one specific data type out of the return
value of the function yeah it's kind of
taking almost that behavior type
approach of like the code does this
thing and then I'm just making sure that
it keeps doing the same
thing kind and and a lot of times if you
go back to like manual testing which I
am a huge fan of exploratory testing but
I am not a fan of traditional manual
testing like manual testing for
regression I am not a fan of but
exploratory testing so manually testing
code much more as a hacker to like gain
insight into like oh here's this thing I
didn't know before I I'm a huge fan of
that and I actually think more and more
as we get AI involved in the code that
we generate right the thing that's going
to become really valuable and
differentiate programmers is not their
programming skills it's going to be
their testing skills there going to be
their ability to say hey Chachi PCH
write me this program and then my
ability to actually verify that that
program is what I want like okay they
wrote this thing is it what I want and I
don't know if you ever played with
prologue at all or any logic programming
but I think chat gpg is moving Us in
that direction and the whole idea of
this is like you are writing the
constraints and then the software is
generating the code and that is what
tddd is right it's like here's my test
write me the system that solves that so
I think the more you've learned to like
craft constraints that then can validate
the better you're going to end up with
code and if we stop writing code we're
still going to be writing the
constraints maybe we're writing them as
unitest test I doubt that I think we're
going to be writing them in prompts but
who knows like predicting the future is
hard do you know how to code are you
looking to supplement your income level
up your career or gain AI experience
have you answered yes to any of these
questions check out data annotation data
annotation pays you to train AI models
by solving and reviewing coding problems
from home on your own schedule apply now
at data annotation ./ programmers that's
data annotation. Tech programmers or use
the application Link in the episode
description on the SEO website at
e-r. okay so like let's take this more
concretely to an example I with a
fantastic developer L and she was
showing me some tests and it's for a
messaging system right so it's like
people call in for customer care and
this system sort of like interacts with
them and gets them to the right operator
there's two things one they're very long
like very often they were 30 40 lines
right and I couldn't figure out like
you'd look at the test and you'd be like
what is this test doing right and then
the other thing is there's a lot of
duplication I am particularly good at
noticing duplication so I'm like okay
the moment I see lots of duplication I'm
like this is a good place for approval
tests and so
as we like started to clean this up we
realized that the essence of the test
was this conversation so you like call
in you're like hey I'd like to pay my
bill and they'd be like oh are you are
you a current customer and the person
would be like yes I am and they're like
great can you give me your customer
number and they're like yeah here you
are and that's the test which really
meant like when we reduced this into an
approval test it was verify conversation
hello I'd like to pay my bill yes I'm a
customer here here's my customer number
that's the input that's the test and
then the output was this file that sort
of showed that conversation user says
this chatbot responds with this user
says this chatbot responds with this
right and it like shows that
conversation so the the output now like
tells me the story and the test is
really easy like it's two lines of code
or one line of code it's verify
conversation and then here's the string
of param that I I am giving and so 30
lines reduces to one line and then
there's multiple tests right so multiple
30 line tests so now instead of like
pages and pages of hundreds of lines of
tests we now have 20 lines of test and
you can very easily scan all 20 tests
and be like that is the conversation
that's causing me pain or I need to
write a new test here's the conversation
that's causing me pain and then when you
look at the approval file that's
associated with the test you you can see
the conversation you can see yeah that's
what I want that's how it should go or
that's not what here's where it went
wrong right because it's a flow of
conversation my immediate thought with
that is is the chat F deterministic
enough that it always outputs the same
thing like it always says hello the same
way because I can see that potentially
causing problem but yes it is however
your point is well taken right like how
do you test something that's
non-deterministic yes that's a good
question yeah I think that that can lead
us back around you had mentioned
printers earlier maybe we can delve into
that a little bit more well so the
printer is definitely one of the ways
right so it could be the chat box or
let's say each of the chats has the time
associated with it right that's going to
be a disaster so you could filter that
out right when you filter that out do
you like replace it with a token that
just says date time or do you just
replace it with nothing or how do you
typically do that so it is actually up
to you the filters are are very very
robust but the standard one the out of
the box one actually replaces it with a
token and a slightly different token
than you might expect so it will say
date and then the number of the date so
date one date two date three and the
reason for that is it's easier to think
about in goids So let's let's use it
with guids so let's say that you have a
piece of Json and it has like a couple
goids in there let's say it has five
goids yeah right I don't just want to
see good good good good because maybe of
those five good
three of them all are pointing to one ah
yeah yeah and the fourth one is pointing
to something else right so you want to
know yeah where it's poting I want to
know so what it will do is it will say
okay I found a guid it has this value
that would be guid one I found another
guid oh it has the same value that would
be guid one too I found a new guid oh
that has a different value that's guid
two and that way you can actually see
the relationship between them and it'll
do the same thing with dates right so if
you have the same date in seven
different places they'll all be replaced
by the token date one if you have seven
different dates yeah and that turns out
to be really useful so that does it on
the filter side and and we use that a
lot but the other thing we do is we'll
say let's restructure the code so the
thing that I notied the most about
people who do test driven development
versus people who do test after is that
the code is more testable right because
if you already have this block of code
then it's like oh I just need to get it
tested and I will do these very
complicated things so I can test it but
if you're like I need to test this code
before I write it then I'll be maybe I I
restructure my code I cut it so it's
easier to test what it means in practice
is often a lot of little methods that
call other methods right so maybe I have
a method that's like generate
conversation and it will say oh call
generate conversation pass it all the
same argument ments but also pass it
today's
date and then I can call it and pass it
the date that I want and now the date is
consistent if we're doing stuff like
stable diffusion testing we'll very
often lock the generative seed right so
if you lock the seed you can get a
consistent generation but by default it
doesn't and so sometimes code is nicely
structured so you can just say okay
here's how I want the random number
generator to be and sometimes there's
like 20 different places where it ask
for a random generator and you'd have to
touch all 20 of those places right so
the more that you start doing this the
more you make your code easy to test and
actually I have this whole saying of
like I don't want my developers to get
good at testing hard code I want my
developers to get good at making hard
code easy to test yeah the edog I always
draw this so I'm an electrical engineer
and this is put on by the i e so they're
all electrical engineers uh like if you
build a circuit board right and you have
a circuit board the stuff on the outer
layers is really easy to access when
you're going to test it because you can
touch a multimeter to read it but if
something's hidden in the middle then
it's basically doesn't exist you can't
directly access it and so part of it is
thinking ahead and adding in those test
points I think about the same way
instead of having one method call right
you've got one method call that calls a
bunch of other methods and you can kind
of pick out the pieces that you want to
test well and there's two parts of that
one is like exposing it so that that
it's easy to get to right and the other
is like exposing information about it
right so like very often I will see code
that has a lot of Setters but no Getters
right I remember the very the I'm going
way back here but when we had flip
phones and we used to write things in
Java 2me right there was ways that you
could like set things on the screen but
you could never ask the screen what it
had ah that made it really hard to test
like I just put a red pixel here is it
actually red or I just changed the font
what is the font but you couldn't ask
for the font you could set the font but
you could request so you can tell they
didn't test that when they wrote it
right because if they did I could have
solved my pain right but they didn't
even solve their pain so very often the
ability to ask your object hey what is
your current state right that seems like
a no-brainer but often it's not there
and then with approval tests we also
usually add let me print your current
state right which for most objects is a
two- string because a remarkably large L
amount of objects don't have two strings
or they have the default two string
which is utter UT garbage in most
language and especially in Java but in
most languages the default two string is
pretty bad it would be nice if the
default two string was
Jason I would love the default two
string of my objects to be Jason that
would be really helpful and these will
show up sometimes in your logs and stuff
where you're like oh it's really hard to
understand that one of the things that I
see show up with approval tests is I
very often will make printers so that I
can test my objects but then sometimes
I'll I'll need to get to a state so
let's let's go back to a game of life
right like I might make it so I can play
with stuff and then get a state that is
useful I would do this so we mentioned
exploratory testing we did a version
like if you look at Conway's Game of
Life online there's like a million
examples of really cool stuff but we
were doing a version of it where instead
of having Square cells they had
hexagonal cells and they were like oh we
would like some cool situations for
hexagonal Conway but there's nothing on
the online for that right so we're like
okay well how do we find interesting
things and so we wrote these tests and
the way they would work is they would
randomly create a board right here's a
100 by 100 board and I'm going to put 10
cells randomly on it and then I'm going
to run it and then I'm going to look for
some property something that I call
interesting so it maybe interesting is a
thousand turns later there's still life
on the board didn't die out or maybe the
thing is every 10 times the board
repeats right or every 12 times 12 is a
nice number right because it could
repeat by one two three four six yeah
right so be like oh is this a thing that
is repeating itself so it just generate
like hundreds of thousands of these and
then look for this trait and if it found
it it would print out okay here's the
board that got us to this well then I
need to take that print out and turn it
back into code this is a concept that
like shows up in Python which I really
like so python has the concept of a two
string but it also has something called
repper and what repper is is the string
of python that's needed to reconstruct
this object so like let me generate the
python code take this paste it into a
python shell and now I've recreated the
object and so this Cycles ends up
showing up in approval testing a lot
where it's like I can use approval tests
to verify my state but then I can
capture that state as starting points
for other tests and Jason does this
naturally right because usually I'm
using some other tool to generate the
Json anyways and that same tool will
take Json and turn it into the object so
that is like those are things I get for
free but sometimes they're more
complicated things that I need it
doesn't really matter the point is that
my ability now to play with my software
and say Here's a scenario I can draw on
a whiteboard how do I test this right
and then how do I actually get the code
to do what I want it to do and see so I
can see that do and often when I see it
I'm like oh uh yeah that's not actually
what I wanted right so like when I see
that HTML show up I'll be like okay yeah
that is what I was trying to do but
that's not what I want and then I can
change it and I can see it again right
so one of the patterns that we saw a
test is these four properties right
which I call specification feedback
regression and granularity specification
is so important to programmers like it's
knowing what it is we're trying to build
and it's really hard to build software
if you don't have any kind of
specification build me some great
software now is that specification come
from the enduser does that come from the
business is it something the developers
create or all of the above hopefully all
of the above however if it gets to the
developer and it has not yet been
created like the buck stops there right
so like if if you ask me to do something
and I can't draw you a scenario I have
two choices I either figure out how to
draw it or I go back to you and we draw
it together both of those are valid
answers right like there's things where
it's like okay let me play oh yeah no
this makes sense and there's other
places where it's like I can't do it let
me go back and get it and there's also I
think there's a third valid which is I
did do it but then I go back and check
just to make sure that this thing I did
is actually what you were saying right
because sometimes like your version of
red and my version of red are not the
same well I think that should always be
part of the process right ideally I
would recommend it I highly recommend it
because again shared pain right if it's
split then we have problems by the time
it gets to the developer I need to be
able to draw a scenario for it in fact
this is a long time ago but we were
creating a web endpoint right and it was
returning some XML and it was me laying
and unfortunately forget the third
person's name but we were in the office
and we're talking we're in this meeting
and they're like okay I think we're on
the same page we got it and I was like
maybe we just draw a sample of what the
XML would look like and they're like ah
we don't have to do that we we
understand it and I'm like yeah yeah but
maybe you can do it for me anyways so
they started drawing the XML and as soon
as they did it they went from violent
agreement to Violent disagree that is
not what I meant as a date that's not no
I need to get a list of things not a
single
so when it becomes concrete you surface
this false agreement right and that's
the place to surf it because if they're
not in agreement what chance do I have
of satisfying them once we're in
agreement then I can do that so that's
all about specification and that's just
us being on a whiteboard I think of this
as testing but it it's not what people
would consider normal unit testing or
anything like that it's not even code at
that point it's just creating the
scenario right and if you give me
requirements those are a horrible way of
translating intent but if you give me a
scenario that's a great way because
people are built around stories right
and also requirements are fuzzy I can
satisfy requirements in multiple
different ways right you can be like oh
build me a hamburger right and
hamburgers basically all satisfy the
requirements but go around to like a
whole bunch of different restaurants and
Order hamburger they are different
things right they're all satisfying the
hamburger requirement but what is the
hamburger you actually want and so when
we get that concrete scenario now we're
like okay that's what we want then I
need to start building it and from there
we move from specification into feedback
and again whether you do traditional
unit testing or not you are going to
want feedback right you're going to want
to know this thing I'm building does it
do stuff maybe you're doing that by
opening a reple maybe you're you're
you're actually opening the app and like
playing around on it but nobody doesn't
execute their software and just ships it
right you you did something you you
opened it in a browser you opened it on
your phone you you did something to get
some feedback that this thing worked and
the more frequent that feedback is the
easier it is the less costly your
mistakes are going to be right and also
there's a discovery that can occur like
if you're interested in the feedback
side of this the person who I think is
by far the best in the world is is a man
named Brett Victor he had a wonderful
talk that you you might have seen
because it was just so insanely popular
called innovating on a principle but he
also has a really nice talk called don't
draw a dead fish he gets upset when
feedback is not instantaneously so if
it's like 500 milliseconds later he's
like that's not good enough like he
wants it to be the moment you touch
anything and a lot of the stuff that
we've seen in development environments
has actually improved because of stuff
that he cares about so he wants this
instantaneous feedback but everybody
cares about feedback regardless of how
how they're timing it once I have
feedback I can build this software and I
can know that I got this thing to work
but then I have this issue of regression
which is okay it worked today does it
work tomorrow and that's is where a lot
of people think I think testing is is a
regression like hey I want to know if I
broke anything and automated tests are
really where regression comes in
although obviously manual tests also are
about regression right
and then there's this last piece of
granularity which is the system broke
why right and just knowing that
something is broken is not enough for me
like I the more I can find out why it's
broken the easier it is for me to fix it
right and so all four of these things
are really important and in the TD cycle
they all get addressed right but whether
you use test first or or even unit tests
you are going to be dealing with all of
these things maybe for granularity
you're using a debugger instead or maybe
you're using logging right to figure out
what's going on maybe you're using
monitoring for regression instead of of
testing you're just like hey for some
reason we didn't make any sales
yesterday there's a canary for
supermarkets which is bananas so it's
like if they haven't sold a banana in
half an hour something is wrong at the
store right cuz like bananas are just a
thing that people buy and they buy a lot
of them frequently and if for some
reason you go half hour with the store
not selling a banana something's wrong
so we use similar things in software
we're like hey is the server up like can
we do a ping can we do a health check
are we not making any sales today or are
we throwing a lot of exceptions all this
goes to monitoring and all of it is good
stuff right but sometimes it's the only
way that you're doing it and then
feedback is the same okay maybe you're
not doing this with automated tests but
if you can write the automated test very
quickly you can get all four of those
things
cheaply and with approval tests it can
be cheaper because you can pull out that
duplication right first of all if we
think about the game of life scenario it
would be hundreds of asserts to validate
what is just a simple animated gif
without the same level of insight it' be
very easy for me to flip oh this should
be at 45 but it actually should have
been at 5'4 right and I wouldn't notice
that in the thing but I'll I'll easily
see it when it prints this graph out the
other thing is when you do have a lot of
spot checks you do these acrobatics
which is like okay I really want to
check that this cell went to this cell
and so what is a scenario where if I
just check this one piece I'll be able
to tell it you create that contrived
scenario scenario exactly right and so
with approval test I don't have to do
that my scenarios are much more what a
business owner would think like so going
they're more like use cases right like
the actual use case because I've done
lots of things where you do an image
processing and you narrow it down to
like okay what's the smallest Square
image like three Square pixels that I
can do or nine square pixels I can do
this thing but really what you want is
when I process the whole image this
thing happens right yes and with an
approval test that is literally verify
image and then here's my starting image
what happens when I run it through this
image processing and then you get the
image back out and you look look at it
and as a human you're looking at you're
like oh I like that let me approve it
that's very easy to recognize it's very
hard to Define image processing is
really really powerful for this because
how would you do it with just a search
like it's almost impossible same with
Sound Processing we were testing
automated voice right so here's some
text it's text to speech so here's some
text I want to verify the sound file
that came out that's really hard to do
with asserts but it's very easy to be
like like it's a again it's a oneline
test verify text to speech here's the
text it's going to create the sound file
and then it will open it up in vcl and
let me actually hear the sound file and
I'll be like oh yeah that sounds pretty
good and I like can approve it although
you know like again going back to
reporters specifically for text for
speech when it would change I would run
it through a reporter that took a sound
file turned it into the graph and then
capture that as an image and then open
it in an image diff so I could see how
the actual wave file changed right like
I want to see how the wave changed
because it could be really hard to be
like I don't understand those sound very
similar to me what what actually changed
I could see for that to doing like a
correlation or something right like
taking the data and actually doing like
the engineering like that cross
correlation and seeing like how similar
are these two wave forms and then maybe
just having a value as long as like as
long as they're within a certain amount
like it's okay it can shift a little bit
because I imagine text to speech is
probably not a very
deterministic no so those we we'd make
it deterministic because right like I
don't what I is like a random seed or
something yeah exactly like so I want it
to be deterministic so I will actually
put into my test so that they are
deterministic but that part of okay I
changed it how did it change am I okay
with this change that's the part where I
want the insight and and like likewise
so I mentioned like the wave files and
stuff but another thing I do really
commonly is I will just print it as a
CVS file right and so now I have a text
file it's a string right it goes really
nicely into my source and stuff but when
things go wrong I'll open it in Excel
and actually start turning it into
graphs and stuff so I can see is this
actually what I want right that can be
hard to know if I get if I get a list of
like 200 numbers is it what I want can
be a complicated question so I again I'm
a programmer so I want to use tools to
help me get insight as to is this what I
want yeah so I think we've done a very
good highle kind of explanation of
testing and how approval testing F let's
spend the last couple minutes and go
into some more details what languages
and Frameworks and stuff does approval
testing support so the answer is a lot
we've been talking about testing but
another part of my life is pair
programming and MOB programming and so I
sort of grew up in the Java and C world
right like those are sort of my
languages and so actually the first
version of approval test I ever made was
in Java and then quickly the second
version was in C but the thing is
because of well in the beginning PA
programming people would come to me and
be like oh this is really helpful i'
would like it in python or I would like
it in C++ or I would like it in Swift
and I'd be like okay let's pair on that
I know approval test really really well
and you know your language really well
and languages are twoo parts right
there's the language and there's what I
would call the culture of the language
this shows up in multiple ways one way
is Clare McCrae who's does a lot of the
C++ approvals with me very often I'd be
like oh I want to do this thing and then
we'd write this code we get the test to
pass and then she sort shake her head be
like oh Luellen that is not proper
C++ right like you you have somehow like
you got it to work but this is shameful
right and then she would show me how to
do it in like idiomatic C++ right
similar thing would occur in Python but
it also like I remember helping my
friend Scott he was a c developer and
he's like I have a Java project I'm just
having a lot of problems with it and so
we open it up and I'm like oh it's a
maven project and he's like how how do
you know that and I'm like oh it has a
palm file and he's like what could I
have Googled to figure that out and I'm
like I got nothing it's super obvious
because I'm in the Java culture but how
do you Google that right so there's a
lot of things that you get that just
because you're in the culture so when I
would pair with people they would bring
like their knowledge of the language and
and more important than their language
knowledge is their culture of the
language right they're the ones who be
like okay this is what idiomatic looks
like in Swift or this is what idiomatic
looks like in Python and so I would pair
with all these people and as as a side
effect approval tests is in quite a lot
of languages and and written by me and
whoever the person is I happen to pair
on that our current list let me just
pull this up because I keep forgetting
so we got it in Java we got it in net we
have it in C++ we have it in PHP we have
it in Python we have in Swift We have it
in JavaScript and in typescript we have
it in Pearl we have it in go we have it
in Lua we have it in Ruby and we have an
Objective C how do you maintain feature
parody across all of those or is it just
kind of like whatever feature somebody
needed in that language we implemented
it and the other ones we just have got
around to yet or so there is definitely
a bit of that right like they are not
all equal and again a lot of this comes
from who I'm pairing with so like some
of the best documentation is in the C++
because Claire really cares about
documentation and we we spend a lot of
time writing documentation but Claire
really cares about documentation and so
I've worked with CLA for many years now
and so there's a little Clare on my
shoulder when I'm in like another
language that still cares about
documentation it's not as good as having
Claire there but but there's like
documentation gets raised on all the
projects because I get to take a little
bit of the people I work with with me
and so very often in you know and
because I would have I'll have standard
meetings that set up a week and so like
on Sundays I'll be working Python and on
Mondays I'll be working Java and then on
Tuesdays I'm working in Swift and what
will happen is we'll develop a feature
in Python that's like nice and useful
and then so on Monday I'll be like oh
hey LS let's do this feature and then
we'll do it and and Lars will show me an
insight and I'll be like oh yeah that's
better and then we'll go to Swift and
I'll be like hey John let's do this
feature and then we'll do it and John
will show me yet another insight and now
so like now the Swift version is
actually the better version right
because it's the third time I've done
this feature so then we come back on
Sunday and I'm like we need to fix we
need to fix what we wrote last time
because I've learned all this stuff in
the iteration right so some of the
feature parody is just happening because
I'm doing iterative development with
different people and I just just did
something and so I wanted to move and a
lot of features actually do Traverse
that way and it it gives a lot more
consistency than you would normally see
in ports right because there's that
shared part then the other part of it is
approval tests unlike normal testing
remember I said like here's how you
verify the frames or here's how you
verify a conversation because there's
that duplication that you can remove
right because it's like here's the
scenario and I'm G to show you the print
out of that scenario this duplication
shows up that doesn't show up in normal
testing Frameworks right you'll see a
little bit of this in cucumber where
you'll have like a custom comparator but
it doesn't show up that much and you'll
see some of it in rspec just because you
can pull up rspec looks like functions
but it's actually not it's it's lambdas
so you can pull like a for Loop above it
or stuff so you'll see a little bit of
it but you don't see a lot of it but in
approval test you see a lot of custom
verify functions give me this thing I'm
going to run this standard process on it
and then I'm going to verify the result
and so for Swift a very standard thing
is I have a a screen or a portion of a
screen and I want to verify the way that
looks on an iPhone that's really a
common scenario in Swift and so here
give me a component and I'll verify it
there's no corollary for that in Python
right so that isn't going to transfer
over so all the custom verify stuff is
is really by language those don't have
parody but the general architecture and
structure those do have parody and I
mentioned we've been doing documentation
and very specifically we've been using
this thing from danela called the four
quadrants of documentation and it's
really really helpful and so the basic
idea is that when you're writing
documentation there are four audiences
that you are talking to right one is a
tutorial tutorial is like I've never
used this thing before and I need to get
it to hello world those things are
ridiculously complicated to write
they're very very detailed
they are I am going to hold your hand at
every step and no matter what when we
are done with this this thing is going
to
work right then there's howtos howt is
basically all of stack Overflow it's
like I have this problem here's how you
solve it right so it's problem recipe
for solution it assumes you have a fair
amount of understanding of the language
it's not handholding you like a tutorial
at all right but it's it's very specific
problem focused then there's reference
references like here's all the stuff the
API does or here's all the different
ways you want to see things with a
reporter you know a lot of times there
are links right or just information
dumping really really useful while
you're programming to be like hey what
are all the methods in this class or
what is this part of reporters what what
relates to that but it's like reading a
dictionary to learn a language they're
helpful if you want to know what a word
means but they're not helpful in general
so so references is complete and its
links but it's not it's not really
trying to teach you anything and then
the last is this explanations and and
the whole reason I'm telling you all of
this is to get to explanations so
explanations a lot of times will talk
about the wise of stuff maybe the
history of stuff the architecture of
stuff right and what we found is those
other three categories are language
dependent but this explanation category
that is a lot more cross language it
doesn't matter the architecture is the
same whether you're in Swift or if
you're in python or if you're in Lua
like it's all the same architecture
right and so as we started to write more
of these explanation Pages we've started
to see a lot more consistency emerge
among the different languages because
we'll be like oh wait a second but that
that doesn't quite apply to like the
JavaScript let's go fix that and that's
one of the things I found with writing
documentation in general test okay so
like and when I started out I didn't
write tests I didn't even know what unit
tests were right I tested my code of
course like I'd run it I'd look at it
but I didn't do any kind of automated
test and then when I got to automated
test the thing that was amazing to me is
you are now using your code we talked in
the very beginning about shared pain
right so like as I try to test my code
and it's hard to test I'm like ouch let
me fix that so it's now easy to test
right and so now I'm like the first user
of my API and so that's good right but
the thing about tests is it's always an
expert user and expert users all look
the same they're knowledgeable like they
get it right when you're writing
documentation you're usually not writing
it from the point of how would an expert
use this code you're writing it from how
would a a beginner learn to use this
code and there isn't just one beginner
there's multiple beginners right when I
wrote test I had empathy for the people
who are using my code but when I wrote
documentation I have empathy for the
people who are learning to use my code
that's a very different person and what
I found is my ego would come into play
the moment I had to document a bad
process so I would be very happy with
like a 20-step install but the moment I
had to document that I'd be like okay
let's write a script that's just install
right like I don't want to have to
document something that's crappy I'm
willing to do something that's crappy
but I don't want to have to document it
so the moment that I have to document
something bad
I will fix it because my ego comes into
play it's like no don't say the
architecture looks like this except for
in JavaScript or it's crappy like go fix
the JavaScript so I can just say the
architecture looks like this right or
don't say like oh but in Swift yeah no
go fix that so you don't have to say
that and so documentation got my ego to
start coming into play for good it's a
very valuable thing I definitely
experienced that recently cuz I I had to
hand a project over to somebody else and
documenting everything because it was me
I I didn't take the time to document
everything as well as I should have and
writing out some of the stuff it's like
oh man you know what before I hand this
to somebody else I better go fix that
thing that I've been living with all
this time and I've been okay with it but
yeah and and there's this other thing
that's come into play with documentation
that is right in board with tests which
is there's a tool that Simon crop made
called MD Snippets it's a really simple
little command line tool that allows you
to put just a little token in some
markdown and then run the tool and it
will expand it by grabbing the code out
of your code base and filling it in and
what that means is my code samples are
all now coming from my unit tests ah
very and that means they say up to date
when I rename St it means if you grab a
code sample it actually works and the
way that markdown Snippets work it also
puts a link to the code so sometimes
you're like well should I fully qualify
the names or not like how much
information does the person need or how
much is just clutter and I no longer
have to make that decision right if they
need more information they can just
click the link it'll take them to the
exact file and they'll be like here's
the whole situation yeah right but
here's just the piece that I think you
need and so markdown Snippets or MD
Snippets allows me to tie together my
tests and my documentation much closer
and I end up writing tests sometimes to
fulfill my documentation right but my
tests are making sure it still works and
and that will go sometimes rather
extreme right like sometimes I'll write
tests that say like because I can do it
with approval test very easily I'll say
like just reflectively look at the
codebase and give me all the calls that
start with the word verify and then I'll
get a list of here are all the verifies
that are in approval test and in their
signatures and then I'll go to my
documentation and say okay here's the
list of all the calls I'll just take the
output of that approval file and include
it into the documentation and then when
I write a new verify function like okay
now we're going to verify like a chat
call then that shows up in my
documentation automatically because my
test detect it my test change it shows
up in Beyond Compare I'm like oh yeah I
did just write that function let me move
it over I approve it it gets committed
my actions my CI kicks in and runs MD
Snippets and says oh this part has
changed automatically updates all I get
all this stuff for free so yeah that's
really great so we talked about
documentation in new users so how would
new users get started using approval
test like what's the first step so
there's two scenarios for new users
because remember I said all new users
are different but the two big categories
are I have an existing project that I
want to add approval test to or I just
want to play with approval tests I want
to start with the user who's like well
this sounds crazy let me try it out so I
can verify that this was a dumb idea the
way I would do that is go to approval
test.com click on the language it will
take you to the GitHub page there and
then all the approval test projects have
a starter project so click the link to
the starter project and just clone that
project and it's a very minimal project
in that l language with like one or two
tests and that will allow you to go from
like there to okay I am now using it in
like a minute or so right so just clone
the starter project open it up and play
with it you want to play with this
that's the way to start if you want to
add it to your existing project that's
going to be language specific but in
general there's a package manager right
so Swift has a package well Swift
doesn't have a package manager per se
but you can easily add a and it points
to the GitHub repo and the line is in
there python has piie net has new git
Java has Maven C++ C++ is an ecosystem
that does not exactly like you so there
are two package managers there's Conan
and VC package it's in there if you're
using those I would just add it that's
the easiest way but often what I find in
C++ packages is that you're just
including the single header file so we
have a download of just a single header
file you can add it to your project
either way you've now added it to your
project then you just call approval.
verify and you pass it your thing right
and most likely when you do this the
first time you're going to get some kind
of garbage right because like I said a
lot of two strings don't there so maybe
you want to actually start with verify
as Json and pass your object there and
then you'll get it as Jason and in the
beginning that's where most people start
so you can think of I've got this array
of things it has 10 elements it's going
to be really annoying to write an assert
for that let me verify it right and then
it'll print out your thing you'll be
like okay yeah that works make sure you
have a diff tool that's going to be
really helpful approval test will
automatically detect it on your system
and it's fairly robust so if you have a
diff tool installed it will probably do
it VSS code works as a diff tool so you
probably at least have that installed as
to stuff like the jet brain Suite so
intell that kind of stuff so it might
just pop up in that so start there and
then you're going to start with the
printers so you're going to start saying
the Json isn't really what I care about
let me describe this show the state of
this object better and so so then you'll
start writing your custom printers and
then you're going to start writing your
custom verifies and that's sort of the
sequence you'll take but you don't have
to add anything other than the approval
testing it works with your current test
framework you don't have to stop using
asserts it plays very well with others
very cool so the website for everybody
to check out is approval test.com and
that's the main place to get started so
thank you so much for giving us this a
great tour of testing and coding
philosophy and approval tests and I feel
like we kind of covered a lot of ground
yeah there's a lot to cover yeah very
good all right thank you very much this
is Sam tager for software engineering
radio have a nice
day thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by It
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at
e-r. to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SE
radio is licensed under creative
comments license
2.5 thanks for